[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Thirty-eight]
[第三十八集]
Given the current potential danger of this career,
由于斗争的需要
[Zhou Enlai, styled Xiangyu, Member of the Tianjin Awakening Society]
[周恩来 字 翔宇 天津觉悟社成员]
all names of the members of our Awakening Society
我们觉悟社社员的姓名
will remain hidden from the public.
对外不公开
So, we will draw from the pool
而用抽签的办法
to give each one a number
以号取名
as a code for communication,
用以作为通信的代号
also as the pseudonym.
和发表文章的笔名
There are fifty notes on the table now.
现在桌子上有五十个纸条
A number is written on each note.
每个纸条上写着一个编号
The number you draw
各位抽到的那个编号
is your future correspondance code and pen name.
就是你今后的通信代号和笔名
Let's start now.
咱们现在开始抓龟
I'm number 36.
我是三十六号
Then I will be called Shanlu from now on.
那我以后就叫衫陆了
I'm number one. My name wil be Yihao.
我是一号 我叫逸豪
[Deng Yingchao, Member of the Tianjin Awakening Society]
[邓颖超 天津觉悟社成员]
I'm number five.
我是五号
I will be Wuhao.
那我就叫伍豪了
Comrades.
同志们
The first activity organized by our Awakening Society.
我们觉悟社成立的第一个活动
is to invite Professor Li Dazhao from Peking University
就是请北京大学的李大钊教授
to come here and give us lectures, guidance.
来我社进行讲演和指导工作
Professor Li is the instructor of the May Fourth Movement in Beijing.
李教授是北京五四运动的指导者
He has rich experience.
有着丰富的斗争经验
We should make full use of this opportunity,
我们要充分利用好这次机会
to learn as much as possible.
虚心向他请教
Tell everyone,
通知下去
[Liu Residence, Luwan, Shanghai]
[上海卢湾柳宅]
the board meeting will be held at eight o'clock tomorrow.
明天八点钟召开董事会
Yes.
是
What's wrong?
夫人
I can't stand it anymore.
我实在是受不了了
I have to go to Beijing.
我得上趟北京
I'm bringing my little girl back whatever the cost.
我说什么也要把囡囡领回来
Calm down.
你先别着急
Darling.
夫人
The situation in Beijing is stable now.
北京的形势现在已经基本稳定了
I believe
我相信我们的女儿
she's safe in Beijing.
在北京是安全的
Besides, our factory is now operating normally.
另外 咱们家的工厂刚刚复工
It's a busy time.
正是忙的时候
I thought they said
我记得他们不是说
that they will come back to Shanghai soon.
不久就要回上海了吗
Don't worry, when they get back to Shanghai
你放心吧等他们回到上海
I will figure out something to stop her from going to France.
我想办法不让女儿去法国了
Wait, you won't let them go to France?
什么 你不让他们去法国了
No.
是
So you're not interested in marrying our daughter into Chen's?
那你不打算攀陈家这门亲了
Not to that family,
动辄进监狱的人
with the dad going in and out jail.
谁敢攀哪
You were the one wanted that marriage.
不是你非要撮合他俩在一起的吗
You said Chen Yannian has a bright future.
说陈延年前途无量
He will be doing great things for the country.
必是国家的梁
Things are different now.
此一时彼一时了
Throughout this May Fourth Movement,
夫人 经过了这次五四运动
I realized a lot.
我真的感悟到了很多新的东西
This country
像我们国家
is based on small-scale production and small-scale peasant economy.
以小生产小农经济为基础
Once there is a large-scale movement from the bottom,
一旦遇上大的群众运动
it can be a disaster
我们这种有身份有资产的人
for people like us with assets and resources.
那就是灭顶之灾呀
I'm worring about our daughter.
我跟你说女儿的事呢
Why are you telling me these?
你跟我说这些事情干吗呀
I have to.
我肯定要跟你说这些事啊
Have you forgotten there's a time
你忘了你那个时候
you couldn't sleep tight at all.
白天晚上你都睡不着觉
You mean during the three strikes.
尔是说闹罢课 搞三罢那阵子
Ah, at that time,
是啊 那个时候
schools and factories went on strike,
工厂罢工 学校罢课
businesses closed.
商铺关门
Didn't all these three strikes
这不是三罢在我们这儿
happen here?
全都有了吗
That month,
那一个多月
I did some calculations.
我算了一笔账
We lost tens of thousands.
我们损失了好几万大洋啊
Wasn't that strike opposing the Paris Peace Treaty?
那不是为了拒签巴黎和约
For patriotism and national salvation?
为了爱国救国吗
You're not being patriotic now.
你又不爱国了
Of course I'm patriotic.
我当然爱国了
I am and
我认为
I am more patriotic than those students.
我比那些学生更爱国
I believe in saving the nation through education,
我崇尚的是教育救国
saving the country depends on industry.
实业救国
Anyway, I have no plan
反正陈独秀这个亲家
in becoming family with the Chen's.
我柳文耀不敢攀
I can't take the risk.
我也攀不起
Say whatever you want, you are a businessman.
说来说去你就是个商人
When it comes to profits and ideals,
一谈到利益
it's always ideal for you.
就顾不上理想了
What is ideal?
夫人 理想是什么呀
In my opinion, ideal is like a lamp.
在我看来 理想就好像是一盏灯
It lights up your heart.
你看着它心里边亮堂堂的
But if you really follow that light,
但是你要真跟着它走
you'll only fall and get injured.
你会碰得头破血流
Moreover, there is no end.
最重要的是 你看不到头啊
Whether this light
走这条路
will lead me to life or death,
是死路还是活路
I have no idea.
我心里没有底呀
[Editorial Department of "New Youth"]
[《新青年》编辑部]
Have some tea.
喝水都自己倒啊
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, Professor at Peking University]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 北京大学教授]
Fellow colleagues.
各位同人
First of all, I'd like say I'm sorry.
首先呢 我要跟大家表达歉意
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library] [Lu Xun, Civil servant under the Ministry of Education]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任] [鲁迅 教育部佥事]
Because of my arrest,
因为我的被捕
"New Youth" has been on a pause for four months.
《新青年》已经停刊四个月了
Now,
现在
our readers
读者 订户
and supporters
还有社会各界
have been calling for the restart of our paper.
要求复刊的呼声很高
They all have high expectations.
期待值也很高
So today, we'll discuss this.
所以今天我们就议议复刊的事
After what happened,
想必经过此番磨难
you must all have some special feelings.
各位心里都有一些特殊的感受
I hope you can share them with the others here.
望各位知无不言 言无不尽
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Then I'll speak first.
那我先说吧
I think the biggest drawback
我认为我们《新青年》
of our paper
最大的弊病就是
is the rotating peer edit chief system.
同人轮流编辑制度
This system has forces
这种制度造成了
every editor to only focus on what he wants.
每一位编辑各行其是
In a way,
破坏了我们
it stops our paper operating as a whole,
《新青年》的整体性
and adds unpredictability to it.
平添了随意性
Shizhi.
适之
Whatever you say needs to be supported by evidence.
你说话要有根据的
Please give us an example.
那请举例说明你的观点
The example is lying around openly for everyone to see.
例子比比皆是 一抓一大把
We are discussing things here,
我们在这儿讨论事情
and we must be right about things, not about people.
一定是对事不对人
Please, Mr. Bannong, don't take it personally.
请半农先生不要自行对号入座
I have no intention of accusing you.
我没有任何指责你的意思
What do you mean? Please speak out.
那你什么意思 请直言
If you insist,
既然你说到这儿的话
I'll speak my mind honestly then.
那我就开诚布公了
For example, Shouchang was the editor on duty.
比如守常当值班编辑的时候
He decided to put out an issue
就自行主编了一期
focusing on Marx's research.
关于马克思研究的专刊
It received a lot of extreme comments
收了很多极端的评论
and extreme feedback.
极端的文章
It caused a lot of trouble.
引来了不少的麻烦
I think such an issue
我认为这样的专刊
does not align with our beliefs
与我们《新青年》
in running this journal.
办刊宗旨是相悖的
Shizhi.
适之
During this period,
这段时间
you have been busy guesting Professor Dewey.
你一直忙着接待杜威教授
There are many things you don't know.
有很多情况你并不了解
Shouchang didn't make that decision all by himself.
守常不是自行主编
That issue on research of Marxism,
他这一期的马克思研究专刊
I knew about it.
我是同意的
Deqian and Yucai also knew.
德潜和豫才也都知道
Yes.
没错
The feedback and comments I have received,
我得到的消息啊
were mostly positive and of high recommendation
各界人士对守常编的这一期
from all walks of life.
其实评价非常高
They said that this issue has brought a new trend
说是给中国的思想界
for the research of ideology in China.
刮来了一股清风
That issue sold very well too.
而且我印象中这发行也特别好
Many Japanese friends also wrote letters,
很多日本朋友也来信
saying they would like to take a look.
说是想要看这一期
Yes, yes, that issue
是是是 这一期
was printed twice.
重复地印了两次
There is not even one copy in stock now.
现在库存连一本都没有了
It's not about how many copies been printed.
印了多少并不能说明问题
When I took over the "Weekly Review",
我在接手《每周评论》的时候
the circulation was also high.
发行量也很高
It still got banned at last.
最后还是被取缔了
[Liu Bannong, Professor at Peking University]
[刘半农 北京大学教授]
Then you should learn from your mistakes.
那你应该检讨自己的失误
Indeed.
对
I learned the lesson.
我就是从教训当中得到了启发
And I think this rotating editor-in-chief system
我认为咱们的《新青年》
is not necessary
不必要再采取这样的
for our "New Youth".
同人轮流编辑制度
If you trust me,
如果大家信任我的话
I will take the job as editor-in-chief.
交给我一个人来编就好了
I will make sure that our "New Youth"
我一定把咱们的 《新青年》
becomes the foremost academic journal in China.
办成中国第一流的学术刊物
Shizhi,
适之啊
you are still holding on your old mindset.
你这还是老生常谈
Let me share my opinion.
我说下我的意见啊
I agree that we should abolish the rotating system,
我同意《新青年》
no more people taking turns being the editor-in-chief.
废止同人编辑轮流值班制度
But I don't agree with Shizhi taking the job.
但是我不同意由适之一个人来编
Why?
为什么
"New Youth"
《新青年》
was brought to life by Zhongfu himself.
是仲甫一个人带来的
Now that Zhongfu has been released,
仲甫现在已经出狱了
I think it should still be returned to Zhongfu.
我认为仍旧应该还给仲甫
He can do the job.
让他一个人去编
Zhongfu, you got this.
仲甫 你就当仁不让吧
We support you as always.
我们是一如既往地支持你
I suggest,
那个我提议啊
whoever supports this proposal please clap your hands.
大家鼓掌通过以下决议
From Volume 7, Issue 1,
《新青年》七卷一号起
"New Youth" will have Chen Duxiu as the editor-in-chief.
仍由陈独秀一人主编
Good.
好
Zhongfu tends to go to extremes.
仲甫那么偏激
Why did you propose
你怎么提议
that he should do the job?
让他一个人编《新青年》呢
Shizhi can be too cautious sometimes,
适之虽然过于小心翼翼
but he is also careful.
但他心细
Things can't go too wrong if he is in charge.
不至于出大纸漏
So you mean
那你的意思是
Shizhi should be editing "New Youth"
让适之一个人
by himself?
去编《新青年》啊
I think he is more suitable than Zhongfu.
我觉得他比仲甫合适
Wrong.
大错
These two people,
这两个人啊
let me give you an analogy.
我给你打个比方吧
If you see their strategy as a warehouse,
假如将韬略比作一间仓库
Mr. Duxiu will set up a large banner in front of the door,
独秀先生会在门前竖一杆大旗
with words written clearly on it:
大书八个字
"Weaponed up, take care",
内皆武器 来者小心
but the door will be left open.
但门是打开的
You can know what is inside with one look, can be few knives or others.
里边有几杆枪 几把刀
Open and clear, no need to worry.
一目了然 无须提防
But when it comes to Mr. Shizhi,
但适之先生呢
the warehouse will be closed
仓库门是紧闭的
with a small note on the door.
门上会有个小纸条
Also with words written on it:
也贴八个字
"Nothing harmful inside, please don't be afraid".
内无武器 请勿疑虑
Of course this note could be telling the truth.
这自然可以是真的啊
But some people, at least people like me,
但有些人 至少像我这样的人
I will always stop and think
我在推门之前
before I reach out and push that door.
我总是会侧头地想一想
So you mean
你的意思
Zhongfu is more reliable, isn't it?
还是仲甫靠谱 是吗
Think for yourself.
自己琢磨吧
Obituary.
讣告
Professor of Chinese Literature in Peking University,
北京大学中国文学门教授
Instructor of the Faculty of Liberal Arts,
文科研究所指导教师
Mr. Liu Shipei, Comptroller of National History Compilation Office,
国史编纂处纂辑员刘师培先生
passed away of illness,
不幸因病辞世
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
at the age of 36.
享年三十六岁
In memory of Professor Liu Shipei
为追思刘师培教授
and his outstanding achievements in the many fields of
在经学 史学 文学
classic studies, historiography and literature,
诸多领域的杰出业绩
a funeral ceremony for Professor Liu Shipei
兹定于今日在妙光阁
will be held today in Miaoguang Hall
举行刘师培教授出祭仪式
hosted by Mr. Chen Duxiu.
由陈独秀先生主持
Many students of the Chinese literature department,
中国文学系诸多同学共同料理
are invited to attend.
恭请北大同人参加
This obituary,
这讣告
I'll have a student later
一会儿就找个同学啊
posting this onto the bulletin board.
给它贴到布告栏去
Zhongfu, thank you for agreeing to host.
仲甫要谢谢你能出面主持
I and Shenshu
我与申叔
always had different political views,
一生政见不同
different academic views.
学术观点也不同
But
不过
we did respect and value each other.
我们彼此倒是有一些喔喔相惜
It is also my wish to see him off.
能送他一程 也是我的心愿
It's such a shame.
申叔太可惜了
Only thirty-six years old.
三十六岁
What about the manuscripts of his works now?
他的那些著作文稿怎么处理现在
I organized a few people
我组织了几个人
to check up and finish his manuscripts
把申叔遗著检齐
and give all those to Peking University Library for preservation.
准备送交北大图书馆保存
That will be my last work
这也算是我作为
as the head of the compilation department
您给我任命的这个
at this job you assigned me to.
编纂处的主任的最后的一份工作吧
Master Cai, I want to...
蔡公 我是想
Zhongfu.
仲甫
The thing is
是这样的啊
now that we lost Shenshu,
申叔一走啊
the National History Compilation Office
国史编纂处啊
has lost its core.
它就倒了一根顶梁柱
What's might happen is that
现在出现个什么情况呢
Xu Shuzheng
徐树这个人哪
wants it take it over,
他想机把它收回去
change it back to the National History Museum,
仍然是叫国史馆
and have it under the management of the State Council.
归国务院领导
If he successes,
如果他要做成了
Zhongfu,
仲甫啊
then the history department of Peking University
那北大历史学学科
will never be what it used to be.
那可就是塌了大半个天
Xu Shuzheng is a warlord.
徐树铮他是个军阀
I can not let him lay his dirty hands on academics.
我不能让他玷污了学问
Zhongfu, you know that.
仲甫 你是知道的
In 1917,
一九 一七年
when I first came to Peking University as the president,
我刚到北大当校长时
it caused me much troubles to take it back
我是硬从范源廉手中
from Fan Yuanlian.
给它要回来的
I reorganized the place,
我进行重组
I personally served as the director.
我亲自兼任主任
All these to
目的
establish the most authoritative discipline of Chinese history
就是要让北大成立一门
in Peking Univeristy.
最具权威性的中国历史学学科
My goal and my ideal is to write a book.
我的理想就是要编写出一部
A book of the correct and thorough history of China.
真正的中国通史
Master Cai.
蔡公
I understand.
我明白您的意思
If this can be done,
我觉得这件事情要是做成了
it will benefit the country and the people tremendously.
也确实是功德无量
It's just that I am now
只是我现在
I...
我想
Listen, listen to me.
你听 你听我说啊
Listen to me.
你听我说啊
Last night,
这个 昨天晚上
I had a good look at Shenshu's
我把申叔以前报上来的
outline of the National History Compilation Office.
国史编纂处的提纲
I read it all.
我看了一遍
I was so excited that I didn't sleep well all night.
我激动得我一晚上都没睡好觉
The part of political history,
他把政治史长编之志
and the part of customs of civilizational history,
和文明史之风俗
these two parts are mostly completed.
这两部分都基本完成了
Thirty-six volumes of political history.
政治史三十六册
Twenty-seven volumes of civilizational history.
文明史二十七册
All of them of high quality.
完成得相当好
He left a lot of valuable first drafts too.
还留下了不少具有价值的初稿
Zhongfu, Shenshu has left.
仲甫 申叔这么一走
This job,
你知道这个工作
no, this project.
那应该说是叫工程了
It's probably gonna just be left aside.
那很可能就要搁浅
I have talked about it to you several times.
我曾经跟你说过多少次了
I also have asked you to take his place in the Compilation Office.
我也请求您能到编纂处来接替他
Because I believe only you have this ability.
因为我相信只有你有这个能力
Because if you don't come
因为你要是不来的话
then this project can never be completed.
那这个工作就基本上是流产了
Master Cai.
蔡公
I thank you for your trust in me.
我谢谢您对我的信任
No, no, no.
不不不
Zhongfu, you and I are brothers.
仲甫 你我都是兄弟
We don't need to use the word thank.
我们何必谈谢字
All I want from you now
我现在就想听你一个
is a clear answer.
准确的回答即可
Master Cai, I have thought about it.
蔡公 我考虑再三
Think about it. Think about it.
你考虑 你考虑考虑
What I just told you,
刚才我跟你说的那些
please think about it a lot.
你多多考虑一下
Master Cai.
蔡公
Sooner or later, I will leave.
我是要走的
At this point,
现在
various schools appeared here in Peking University.
北大已经形成了各个学派
That reform plan we made together at the beginning,
我当初跟您一起制订的改革计划
most of it has came true.
也都巴经实现了
It's time for me to go.
我该离开北大了
I am speaking from the bottom of my heart.
我说心里话
I knew.
我是知道
I knew your answer before you stated talking.
你是会有这种回答的
I knew Peking University is too small a stage for you.
我明白北大这块舞台太小
You are a free-spirited person who aims big.
你是个天马行空 无拘无束的人
You deserve to shine on a bigger stage.
应该到更大的地方去发展
I remember
我此时此刻我想到
how it was snowing heavily that year.
那年大雪纷飞
The year I welcomed you to Peking University.
我迎先生到北大来
Now it's autumn, winter is right at the corner.
如今天凉入秋
But I have to see you off this time.
我却要送先生离开
It's hard.
不好受
Nevertheless.
当然
Zhongfu, I know that you will always be a part of Peking University.
仲甫 我坚信你是北大的人
Please believe that wherever you go,
请你相信无论你走到哪儿
Peking University and Cai Yuanpei
北大和我蔡元培
will always have your back.
都是你仲甫的后盾
Yannian.
延年
One second.
稍等一下
Go to your uncle Shouchang first.
你先去找你守常叔叔
I'm gonna walk around a bit.
我自己走走
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
Yes.
行
Let's go.
走吧
You guys gather together here.
你们几个凑一堆
Where are you going?
这是要去哪儿啊
Where can we go?
能去哪儿啊
You leaving Peking University.
你离开北大
[Qian Xuantong, styled Deqian, Professor at Peking University]
[钱玄同 字 德潜 北京大学教授]
We came to see you off.
我们来给你送行
Where is Shizhi?
适之呢
Five ministers are going abroad.
五大臣出国
Shizhi is busy seeing them off.
适之张罗着欢送去了
What do you mean by five ministers going abroad?
五大臣出国 什么意思
Shizhi used that sponsored fund from Mu Ouchu,
适之用穆藕初的赞助
and sent Luo Jialun, Duan Xipeng and other three people
为罗家伦 段锡朋等五人
to study in the United States.
办成了赴美留学
People here in Peking University joke that five ministers went abroad.
北大人戏称五大臣出国
There are many students studying abroad recently.
最近出国留学的很多呀
That's right.
可不是嘛
Fu Sinian did not make it into the five ministers.
傅斯年没有挤进五大臣之中
Shizhi managed to find a way,
适之就想办法
got him a quota in Shandong.
在山东给他搞了一个名额
Now Fu has left to the United States too.
现在人也去美国了
[Gao Yihan, Professor at Peking University]
[高一涵 北京大学教授]
Xu Deheng and the others
还有许德珩等人
went to France for work-study.
是去法国勤工俭学
The pioneers of the May Fourth Movement have all left.
五四运动的先锋都走了
It feels like the curtains has come off after all.
让人感觉有点秋风萧瑟的味道
I hope they will all take the right path.
但愿他们都能走上一条正路
I'm going to England, too.
我也要去英国了
I knew.
我知道
Bannong, I wrote you this.
半农 我给你写了一幅字
I wanted to bring it to you specially.
本来想专程给你送过去
Since we are all here to say goodbye,
既然在这儿告别
I will give it to you now.
那现在就给你楼
You are one with strong ambition,
本有冲天志
driven by that you walk all over this country's land.
飘摇湖海间
You found this place and decided to stay.
偶然憩城郭
But it's only a temporary stop after all.
犹自绝追攀
I see what this long journey has done to you.
寒影背人瘦
Your body suffered but your mind gained.
孤云共往还
One day we will realize our dream
道逢王子晋
and get to live in peace ever after.
早晚向三山
I feel reluctant to part with you here
有点舍不得这里 舍不得你
and to leave our "New Youth".
舍不得咱们的《新青年》
"New Youth" will always be there.
《新青年》还在
From now on, you will be an oversea peer editor
你现在就是《新青年》的
for "New Youth".
海外同人编辑
We are still on the same side.
我们还在一条战壕
I hope that
希望
you can still write for "New Youth"
你还能再给《新青年》写文章
especially with your poetry.
特别是你的诗歌
Now it can be said that no one can match it.
现在可说 无人能及了
You flatter me.
仲甫兄谬奖了
I will try my best.
我一定努力
Zhongfu.
仲甫
Brother Jigang.
季刚兄
You give up the promising job of working as a professor.
你说你放着好好的教授不做
You just have to leave and attend to that journal of yours.
你偏偏却要去编那个
A journal that might go nowhere.
不伦不类的杂志
Without you,
你这一跑
China is missing a great book of general history.
中国便是少了一部通史啊
What a loss this is!
这是多大的损失
Have you ever thought about this?
你可曾想过这个问题
Brother Jigang, you have your academics.
季刚兄 你做你的学问
I have my journal.
我搞我的不伦不类
As for whether it is a loss.
至于是不是损失
Time will prove it.
历史自有公论
Hopeless.
不可救药
Goodbye, brother Zhongfu.
别了 仲甫兄
Zhongfu
仲甫
Will you still fight even when you go somewhere far away?
君去也 还斗否
If there's still a breath, there's still fighting.
一息尚存 战斗不止
Brother, take care. Take care.
贤弟保重 保重
Brother Tangsheng, take care.
汤生兄 珍重
[Liu Bannong, pioneer of the New Culture Movement, literary scholar, linguist, and educator. Died in Beijing in 1934, aged 43.]
[刘半农，中国新文化运动先驱，文学家，语言学家，和教育家。1934年在北京病逝，享年43岁。]
[Huang Kan, famous linguist and philologist. Died in Nanjing in 1935, aged 49.]
[黄侃，著名语言文字学家。1935年在南京病逝，享年49岁。]
[Gu Hongming, famous translator. Died in Beijing in 1928, aged 71.]
[辜鸿铭，著名翻译家。1928年在北京病逝，享年71岁。]
Shouchang.
守常
This is my official farewell to Peking University.
我这算是正式地跟北大告别了
From now on,
从今以后
I will concentrate on "New Youth"
我会专心地编辑《新青年》
and social activities.
和搞社会活动了
All these years passed,
转来转去
you ended up being a professional revolutionary again.
你现在又成了职业的革命家了
I admire you!
美慕你呀
Shouchang, "New Youth" is back again.
守常《新青年》还要复刊
I think after all that happened,
我想 经历了这么多磨砺
It should have a new look.
它应该是一个薪新的样子
I want to write another manifesto
我想再写一篇宣言
and show it to the world.
展现给世人
I think we should listen to
我觉得我们应该听听
what young people have to say.
那些青年人的意见
They are the future.
他们才是未来
That's right.
说得很对
How about this?
你看这样行不行
You know Yannian and Qiaonian are going to France.
正好延年 乔年也要去法国了
I keep telling them
我一直跟他们说
that I would take them to the Great Wall.
要带他们去长城看看
But I didn't have time.
总是挤不出时间
It's late autumn now.
眼下 正是深秋之际
Autumn wind seizes the north.
骏马秋风塞北
Leaves turning red.
霜林染醉
We should take the young ones, go to the Great Wall.
我们约上青年人
How's that sound to you?
一同去逛逛长城 如何
Witnessing history and nowadays at the Great Wall,
城头无限今古
along with the beautiful scenery.
眼前方里关山
Perfect time and perfect location.
情境俱佳
Ma Jun and Zhou Enlai
天津的马骏还有周恩来
started a club in Tianjin.
成立了一个觉悟社
They invited me to give a speech tomorrow.
让我明天去给他们讲讲
So how about this weekend?
我们周未如何
Good.
好
[Great Wall, Beijing]
[北京 长城]
Boys and girls.
同学们孩子们
Yannian, Qiaonian.
延年乔年
When I first arrived in Beijing,
刚到北京的时候
I told them that
我就告诉他们两个
be sure to visit the Great Wall.
一定要来看看长城
Standing at the Great Wall
登上长城
will broaden your horizons than ever.
会有助你纵览古今 放眼寰宇
They are going to say goodbye today.
今天他们将要辞亲别友
Leaving home and heading for a long trip.
去国远行了
This tour here
大家相携在此一游
is the perfect farewell for us.
可谓壮别
This is where you see and remember your hometown,
何处望神州
and crave this scene in your mind.
满眼风光看故楼
The Great Wall.
长城啊
The Great Wall,
长城
a barrier built to defend against foreign enemies
曾经是我们的先人
by our ancestors.
梦想抵御外敌的一道屏障
But have you ever thought about it?
可是大家有没有想过
In Qing Dynasty or in this Republic of China,
无论是清朝还是民国
with all those people holding great ambitions,
多少志士仁人
all those people who sacrificed one's life to save the country.
舍身救国血流漂
Why this country
为什么我们这个国家
with walls of thousands miles
空有这残垣万里
is broken like this.
至今却依然是疮康满目
We keep losing and keep being bullied,
在这个强盗的世界里
in this world where the robbers can always have their way.
一败再败 任人欺侮
What is the method to strengthen this country?
富国强兵之路 竟在何方
Mr. Zhongfu, we all think
仲甫先生 我们都认为
we should stand out
我们应该勇敢地站起来
and destroy the old world.
把旧世界打个落花流水
Good point!
说得好
It is time to get rid
世界上的军国主义和金力主义
of militarism and capitalism from this world.
现在是应该抛弃的了
Our ideal new society
我们理想的新社会
is honest, progressive, positive,
是诚实的 进步的 积极的
free, equal, creative,
自由的 平等的 创造的
beautiful, kind, peaceful,
美的 善的 和平的
where people mutually love and help each other,
相爱互助的
where people pride their labor and enjoy working,
劳动而愉悦的
where the whole of society is happy,
全社会幸福的
hoping all those false,
希望那虚伪的
conservative, negative,
保守的 消极的
shackled, class-based, inherited,
束缚的 阶级的 因袭的
ugly, evil, war-like,
丑的 恶的 战争的
lazy, sentimental, and boring,
轧练不安的 懒情而烦闷的
where only a few get to live happily,
少数幸福的现象
will gradually vanish and be destroyed.
渐渐减少 至于消灭
We shall be friendly with
我们对世界上各种民族
people from all races, from all ethnicities in the world.
都应该表示友爱的情谊
But for aggression
但对于侵略主义
and possessive individualism,
和占有主义的军阀和财阀
we will treat them as enemy.
我们不得不以敌意相待
Our ideal is a movement of the people,
我们的主张是民众运动
a social transformation.
是社会改造
We must cut ties with
要和过去以及现在各派政党
any past and present political parties.
绝对断绝关系
We believe in true democracy,
我们相信真正的民主政治
we want to allocate political power to the people.
必会把政权分配给人民大众
Wealth will no longer be seen as a criterion to decide if one is good or bad.
不以财富有无为标准
We oppose all political parties which support interests of only a few,
我们反对一切拥护少数人私利
or of a specific class,
或一阶级利益
or when it does not consider about the common happines for the people.
眼中没有全社会幸福的政党
Students, since the Opium War,
同学们 自鸦片战争之后
we Chinese people have been on a long journey looking for a solution.
我们中国人为了寻找救国的药方
It's been eighty years.
已经有八十年了
We have tried whatever we can.
可以说是尝遍了各种药方
But today,
但是今天
on this ancient Great Wall,
在这个古长城上
I and Mr. Zhongfu
我和仲甫先生在你们的身上
found hope.
看到了这个曙光
Students.
同学们
You are the pioneers of this era.
你们是这个时代的先锋
I hope that with the strength of youth
我希望你们以青春的力量
you will realize the great ideal of socialism.
去实现社会主义的伟大理想
You will rebuild the great glory of our nation.
去重建我们这个民族的伟大辉煌
Enough from us two.
别听我们两个在这儿演讲了啊
Go and enjoy the Great Wall.
你们各自去感受长城
Yes.
好
The sky is boundless just like our ambition.
楚天干里清秋
This scenery before us is endless just like our life.
水随天去秋无际
The sun shines upon the ground,
落日楼头
birds us departure to somewhere far away.
断鸿声里
We are all strangers on foreign land,
江南游子
with all our dreams and thoughts, no matter where we go and who we meet,
把吴钩看了 栏杆拍遍
no one will truly understand.
无人会 登临意
Let's go.
走吧
See who climbs up first.
看谁先爬上去
Shouchang.
守常
Did you know,
你知道吗
I spent more than three months in prison.
我在牢里面待了三个多月
During the time, I focused on reading books and materials
我重点读了社会主义学说
on the theory of socialism
和俄国十月革命的
and the October Revolution in Russia.
一些书籍和资料
I can say that now
我现在可以确切地告诉你
I have a deep understanding
对于马克思主义学说
of Marxism.
我有了进一步的认识
Tell me about it.
说说
Wait a minute.
你等会儿
I-I need to talk to you.
我我 我有话跟你说
What is it?
什么话呀
I'm going to France soon.
我马上要去法国了
Do you want to marry me?
你娶了我吧
Comrade Yi.
不是 易同志
Didn't we both agree?
咱们俩不都说好了吗
We are comrades.
咱们俩就是同志
We can't be that kind of relationship.
不可能发展成那种关系
Besides, you are going to France soon.
再说了 你马上都要去法国了
We don't even know if we can meet or not,
咱们俩以后能不能见面
or when we can meet.
什么时候能见面也说不准呢
I will ask you one last time.
我最后问你一遍
Yes or no?
娶还是不娶
Qunxian.
群先
Comrade Qunxian.
群先同志
I swear on the Great Wall,
我对着长城发誓
I can't marry you.
我不能娶你
Dont be like this please.
你别这样
I'm gonna cry on this Great Wall.
我去哭长城去
When the Great Wall collapses over my tears,
哭倒了长城
you will be buried underneath it.
砸死你
Although now,
虽然现在
I'm not quite sure yet.
我还没能十分肯定
But generally speaking,
但是大体上
I have a preliminary concept in my mind.
已经有了一个初步的概念
That is,
那就是
maybe only Marxism
也许只有马克思主义
can save China.
可以救中国
Maybe there is only the road of Russian October Revolution
也许只有俄国十月革命的道路
that can save China.
才能救中国
I can deeply relate to you now.
仲甫兄登临之意岂无人会
Feels like we are witnessing light shining upon this country.
为霞满天哪
I want to cheer for you
我真是想为你这个思想升华
for you eventually come to realize it.
大声喝彩
I really want to shout loudly at the Great Wall.
我真是想冲这个长城大声呼喊
There is hope for China after all.
中国有救了
That's also why I said
所以我说
for the re-issue of "New Youth",
《新青年》复刊
we should focus on publicizing and introducing Marxism,
要重点宣传和引进马克思主义
we should publicize and study the Russian October Revolution.
要宣传和研究俄国十月革命
The goal of our "New Youth" will be transferred
要把办利的重点
from enlightment
由原来的思想启蒙
to looking for the road to save the nation,
转到探寻救国的道路
to realize the fundamental transformation of society.
实现社会的根本改造上来
Look at it.
这边看
I've made a formal application.
我已经正式提出申请了
Next semester,
下一个学期
I want to start a class of historical materialism
我要开设唯物史观
and a class of the international workers' movement.
和国际工人运动这两门课
At the same time, I also want to establish a Marxist theory research society.
同时我还要建立马克思学说研究会
I want to be ready so that one day in the future
为将来提供一个政治性组织
we can establish a political organization.
做好准备
Good. Shouchang.
好 守常
You are thinking in long term here.
还是你想得长远
After the May Fourth Movement
五四运动这个事件之后
there is some questions
我们确实有些问
that we need to reconsider about.
需要想得深一点了
The key is
关键是
we want to rebuild a country,
我们要重新再造一个国家
we want to create this new country
再造一个薪新的国家
where all the people
而且要让国人
can live a happy life.
生活在幸福的生活里
Good point!
说得好
This is also the gist of the reissue declaration
这也是我们 《新青年》
for "New Youth".
复刊宣言的主旨
Shouchang, I'm really happy today.
守常 我今天真的很高兴
The youth should pursue this course,
青年循蹈乎此
be rational and endeavour,
本其理性 加以努力
go forward and not look back,
进前而勿顾后
shun the dark and face the light,
背黑暗而向光明
to advance civilization for the world,
为世界进文明
to create happiness for all mankind,
为人类造幸福
with a youthful self,
以青春之我
create a youthful family,
创建青春之家庭
a youthful country,
青春之国家
a youthful nation,
青春之民族
a youthful mankind,
青春之人类
a youthful Earth,
青春之地球
a youthful universe,
青春之宇宙
to enjoy one's endless life.
资以乐其无涯之生
Our ambitions and aspirations, lie distant and far.
乘风破浪 迢迢乎远矣
For what is to worry
复何无计留春
of not forever keeping the spring?
望尘莫及之忧哉
Yannian.
延年
Qiaonian.
乔年
You are going to work and study in France.
你们就要去法国勤工俭学了
You have been waiting for five years.
酿了五年
Good things are worth waiting.
好事多磨
Before you go,
临行
I still have a few words to tell you.
还是有一些话想跟你们说
You know what I am like,
你们了解我的为人
I have to say what's on my mind.
不说我得慌
As far as I know,
据我所知
the war in has ended and now there is an economic depression.
欧战结束 经济萧条
France has a high unemployment rate at the moment.
法国失业率很高
More importantly,
更为重要的是
their current national government is nothing but a showcase.
他们现在的国民政府是个空架子
They don't have sufficient financial resources
没有财源
and live by borrowing money from foreign countries.
是靠向外国借钱过日子
At time like this, is such a government-funded Sino-French university
这样的政府资助的中法大学
reliable?
靠得住吗
So,
所以
you need to prepare for in case there is no university to go to.
你们要有上不了学的思想准备
But Mr. Wu Zhihui...
吴稚晖先生
Will you hear me out?
你听我说完 好吗
To be honest, for this work-study program,
说实话 对于去法国勤工俭学
I am not fully supportive.
我是持保留意见的
Thousands of people go there all at once,
一下子几千人过去
they can't speak the language well,
语言又不过关
and there is not enough money.
又没有充足的经费
It's impossible that everyone of them can go study in the school.
不可能大家都有学上
If that happens,
弄不好就很可能成为
it will cause a big social problem.
很大的社会问题
We are mentally prepared for difficulties.
我们对困难有思想准备
Don't worry about that.
这个您不必担心
I worry.
我担心
I'm worried about more than that.
我担心的还不仅仅是这些
I worry about your faith too.
还有你们的信仰问题
You don't have to worry about this either.
这个您也不必担心
I and Qiaonian
我跟乔年
are both people of faith.
我们俩都是有信仰的人
I know, especially you, Yannian.
我知道特别是你 延年
I know you have already done deep study and research
我知道你对无政府主义
on anarchism.
已,经有很深的研究和理解了
You even organized an evolution club in Shanghai
在上海跟黄凌霜等人
with Huang Lingshuang and others.
还组织成立了进化社
You were the editor-in-chief of "Evolution Monthly and Series",
主编《进化》月刊和丛书
you were even wanted by the government and the patrol house.
还遭到了政府和巡捕房的通缉
I understand that
我都知道
our motive is to save the country.
你们的动机是爱压 救国
But,
但你们对
you are too obsessed with anarchism.
无政府主义的执看和偏爱
That's what I'm worried about.
也是我担心的
Our choice of faith has been through
我们对信仰的选择
a long period of comparison and verification.
是经过长期的比较和验证的
I have also undergone long-term comparison and verification.
我也经过了长期的比较和验证
Yannian
延年
I also tried to
我也曾经试图
use the theory and principle of mutual aid theory
试图用互助论的理论和原则
to save China.
去拯救中国
But will it work?
可是行得通吗
Have you ever thought about it?
你有没有想过
The work-study mutual aid society you started at first.
你们最初办那个工读互助社
What is the real reason for its failure?
失败的真正原因是什么
I thought... I now think that
我以为 我现在以为
that the true reason
本质的原因
is that it won't work trying to fix this country
是一点一滴地去改良中国
little by little.
行不通的
If China wants to strengthen itself
中国要想自强
it must go through
就必须要经过一场
a continuous, large-scale revolution.
持续性的 革命性的大变革
Isn't it too early for you to draw this conclusion?
您现在下这个结论还为时尚早吧
Not at all.
不早
We have been wandering around cluelessly for a long time.
我们排的时间已经很长了
We are now at this point,
我们已经到了
when we have to make up our mind.
非下决心不可的时候
Yannian. Qiaonian.
延年  乔年
I just hope you won't be stubborn
我只是希望你们不要太固执
and blind yourself with only one theory.
太迷信一种理论
If only you can take sometime
抽时间有时间去读一读
to read about Marx's works,
马克思著作
to study the present situation of Soviet Russia.
去研究一下苏维埃俄国的现状
Don't deny it before you learn about it.
不要一味地排斥
Okay?
行吗
We accept your suggestion.
您的这个建议我们接受
Okay.
好
As a father,
作为父亲
I should have cared for you.
我本应该呵护你们
I should have made sure that you grow up healthily and live safely.
健康成长 平安生活
But as a father,
可是作为父亲
how much I wish
我有多希望
that the three of us
我们父子三人
will one day
能够有一天
fight in the same trench.
在同一条战壕里面
We will be able to work together
为我们这个多灾多难的国家
for this country in trouble.
去做一点事情
This is also what we hope.
这也是我们希望的
Good.
好
Pack your things.
你们收拾东西吧
Last week, Chen Duxiu moved out his stuff
上周 陈独秀搬走了
left in Peking University.
他的北大的办公用品
He went to the Great Wall
周未又和李大钊等人
with Li Dazhao in the weekends.
起去了长城
Yesterday, he gave a lecture in a normal university.
昨天他在高等师范做了报告
This is the content of the report.
这是报告内容
People like Chen Duxiu,
陈独秀这种人啊
you have to keep an eye on them,
町还是要的
but how to do it is not that simple.
但这即人是要有学问的
you can't let him out of your sight
既不能让他脱离你的视线
[Wu Bingxiang, Chief of the Metropolitan Police Department]
[吴炳湘 京师警察厅总监]
but you can't have him notice too.
又不能让他发现你
Especially now,
尤其是现在
it's the North-South Peace Period.
南北议和时期
We can't have anything goes wrong because of him.
不能因为他再出了什么乱子
However,
不过呢
as long as nothing big happens,
最近只要不出什么大事的话
you can also relax a bit.
还可以放松一下
You all worked hard.
兄弟们也辛苦
Remember, as long as nothing big happens.
那个 以不出事为原则
Understood.
明白
Go now.
去吧
I will excuse myself.
属下告退
Selling newspapers! Selling newspapers!
卖报卖报
Look at the new issue of "New Youth"!
看新复刊的《新青年》
New declaration for the paper!
发表本志宣言
New political ideas!
提出新的政治主张
New social ideals!
和社会理想
Read newspaper!
看报了 看报了
Newspaper!
卖报了 卖报了
Look at the newly published "New Youth"
看新出版的《新青年》
New declaration for the paper!
发表本志宣言
Please have one, sir.
先生 要一份吧
Newspaper!
卖报了 卖报了
Look at the newly published "New Youth"!
看新出版的《新青年》
Please.
请进
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
Mr. Zhongfu is here.
仲甫先生来了
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
Master Cai.
蔡公
Come.
来来来
You wanted to see me.
您找我
Please sit down.
你请坐
Brother Zhongfu.
仲甫兄
Shizhi.
适之
Come, come, sit here.
来来来 坐这儿来
Okay.
好 你去
Zhang Shizhao sent a telegram.
章士钊 发来一封电报
I wanted to send it to you.
我本来想给你送去的
But I was talking business with Shizhi, couldn't find the time.
后来呢 我跟适之在谈事走不开
So I invited you here.
我就请你过来了
Take a look.
你看一眼
Xingyan sent this from Guangdong.
这行严从广东打来的
He is now the general secretary in the southern government.
行严现在是南方政府的秘书长
He's also the representative of this North-South peace talks.
也是南北议和的代表
He said that
他说呀
the Southern government has approved
广东车政府已经批准了
Chen Jiongming's plan,
陈炯明的方案
they will start to work on establishing Southwest University.
崔备要筹办西南大学
Zhang Shizhao and some others
委托章士钊等人
along with us two are entrusted as the one responsible for
还有我们两个人作为筹办员
the establishment plan for the Southwest University.
去负责西南大学的筹备方案
Zhang Shizhao said
章士钊说呀
he wants you to
他说 希望你呀
go to Shanghai to meet him,
到上海去一趟与他见面
then go to Guangzhou.
然后再去广州